i am peter limberg the steward of the
stoa
and today is part of a series a sense
maker in residence series at the stoa
um it's what we're having here we have
someone who's trying to make sense of
the world
visit the stoa for four sessions over
four weeks
the same day the same time each week to
share their thoughts on a certain theme
and the idea is to build a discussion
throughout the month and we had
john robb a military analyst just end
his sense maker in residence for
august upcoming ones we have peter wang
zack stein bonita roy daniel
schmuckerberger nora bateson
many more and today we have the one and
only
everyone's favorite sense making bad boy
from wales
dave snowden uh here today and in a
moment we will
formally give a more robust introduction
of dave
uh but with how this year is gonna work
we're gonna have a facilitator mc for
each
series so i'll introduce the series and
then the mc will take over from here
and today we have cleal martin uh clear
martin's an engineer and data scientist
in toronto canada and he's facilitated
many sessions
at the stoa such as the metagame
mastermind and the dark stoa
so i'll hand it over to cleo clear we'll
introduce david and tell and say how
this
today's session is going to work so that
being said cleo
i will take you in thanks peter
um how's my audio i'm doing okay it's
good
great i just want to welcome back dave
um he was here in april is that right
dave um
for you i'm i'm sure most of you guys
uh were here um
let me know who was here it wasn't but
yeah you guys should definitely check
that out it's
up on youtube uh for those who don't
know dave snowden he is a pioneering
uh management consultant and researcher
in the topics of sense making and
anthro complexity more broadly um
he's a very industrious man with an
interesting past um
and i hope we can learn more about that
past um in
the following sessions um his work
moves up and down the social stack from
ethnography to
global policy and i would say that
he has one of the most compelling voices
in the paths between
humanities and heart sciences and the
true
in the true spirit of complexity science
and i think that's what we're going to
talk about
uh today so without further ado i'll
hand it over to dave
uh well maybe i can ask startup for the
question
for you unless you have something
prepared right off the bat if no
okay go for it okay so
i guess how how what would you describe
your role in civilization as what
what is your vocation what are you what
do you call yourself
uh that's a difficult one um
i think what i'm trying to do um overall
is to bring a science-based approach to
sense making
all right and there are various reasons
i think that's important
but i mean let me just summarize i don't
think we ever lived in a fact-based
society i think the idea
we're in the post-fact society is
actually nonsense yeah
we never lived in a fact-based society
people normally delegate decision-making
but really from the 1940s onwards we
kind of
just assumed that the experts knew what
they were doing
and that really hasn't panned out for a
lot of people so we're trying demagogues
instead at the moment all right and
that's going to get really nasty
so from my point of view i think there's
a sort of rationality in the way
we make decisions at an individual level
a company levels of society level
which we desperately need to find a new
way of working for
and from my point of view i think the
the discovery of complexity science
which happened more or less within my
lifetime
yeah um and it is
i'm running around a bit at the moment
but alicia gerard and i once sat down
this if you haven't read gerar's stuff
on
on complexity she's one of the the
authors and one of the best people i
know
and we're both philosophers by
background although i didn't do a
doctorate under seal which she did so
that's definitely one up
all right we said one of the great
things about complexity science
is it allows multiple multiple
incompatible ontological states to
coexist
and that actually resolves a hell of a
lot of problems
in philosophy so alyssia
um famously in a book dynamics in action
resolves the old dilemma
of when is a winker blink and i spent
a term of my life at university writing
essays about that
and it's kind of like an important
distinction if you don't get it right in
a bar late at night you might get your
face slapped
right so and it's a problem with
intentionality
yeah so intentionality free will once
you start to realize
there are systems which have inherent
uncertainty
and critically don't have material
linear your causality
you start to get a very different basis
on which you make decisions
and my definition of sense making is how
do we make
sense of the world so that we can act in
it
now um overall it's now recognized as
one of the five schools of sense making
um i mean the great granddaddy of all of
this
is carl vike um vipe really comes out of
the sort of
u.s sociological tradition it's all
about retrospective coherence
it's observational derivation of theory
and i'll come back to why i'm
didn't take that approach here um you've
got
dervin who comes from library science
have a huge amount of respect for brenda
and some of the time i've spent
with her has been you know some of the
treasured times of my life
both in frisco and her to home she's
really coming from an information
science post-modernist background
yeah in terms of the way she thinks and
you've got gary klein who i can also
count as a friend in fact i used a lot
of work from gary cline
um who is kind of like into the whole
mantle models thing
he was the guy who discovered
experimentally how people make decisions
which is a key part of my work yeah
through observation of firefighters and
aircraft guys
so he was a gun guy who discovered
experimentally the pattern basis of
human decision making
so we scan and and i can now go into the
harder science on this gary did it
observationally
i did it by talking with a whole bunch
of cognitive neuroscientists
we scan about five percent of the data
that's available to us on a good day if
we're really focused
um normally it's a lot less than that
if you're chinese the figure doubles
um typically really focus somebody from
a chinese background
will actually scan about 10 um
we think the evolutionary difference for
that is the difference between symbolic
and
literal languages so in if you're
speaking mandarin you have to understand
the context of every symbol to
know what it means so if you look at
some of the other experiments on this
chinese students shown a picture of a
tiger drinking from a stream in the
forest
we'll remember the forest and will often
miss the tiger
american students will nearly always see
the tiger and mr forrest
it's like a context object the
difference
yeah so if we take the epigenetic effect
of language we know that's sort of been
built into biology
right so we can see that difference but
you know for all human beings whatever
background we're scanning a fragment of
what's available to us
and we then do a first fit pattern match
with previous experience
uh not a best fit to first
all right and this is called this is
combo stuff this is called conceptual
blending
what we do is we take a partial stimulus
and then we blend it together with
various
memories yeah and extended memories and
group memories
which are triggered by that observation
and we blend together those memories
and decide what to do and that's how
all human beings make decisions unless
they're fully autistic
at which point they scan everything and
they can't cope
that literally can't go yeah and because
the volume overload
now you can see why this happens in
evolutionary terms if you think about
the early hominoids on the savannas of
africa
or possibly the south the mediterranean
sea they're starting to get disputed at
the moment
um something large in yellow with very
sharp teeth runs towards you at high
speed
do you want to autistically scan all
available data
look up a catalogue of the flora and
fauna of the african belt
and have an identified lion look at best
practice case studies on how to deal
with lions yeah
uh by that time the only document of any
use to you will be the book of jonah
from the old testament
which is the only written example i've
found of how to escape from the
digestive tract of a large carnival
yet written by a purported survivor
so we evolved to make decisions very
very quickly based on a partial data
scan
privilege in our most recent experiences
now if that's the way we make decisions
what patterns we use
are then critical and what i'm going to
probably do on
the third one of these is talk about the
work we're doing with distributed
ethnography
um effectively to present multiple
patterns
right so that we can actually pre-filter
the data
by presenting things from different
perspectives
i mean the other famous experiment on
this which i referenced in the april
talk is the
the radiologists given a batch of x-rays
asked to scan for anomalies and on the
final x-ray a picture of a gorilla
is placed in plain sight which is 48
times the size of a cancer nodule
and on average 83 of radiologists don't
see it even though their eyes physically
scan it
they do not see what they're not
expecting to see
now most of the time this makes perfect
sense it's very rarely that people have
miniature gorillas in their lungs
and therefore it's unlikely to occur
anyway right so
we need to realize and this is another
coming back decline klein argues very
strongly we shouldn't talk about
cognitive biases i agree with him
we should talk about cognitive
heuristics
uh evolution doesn't throw out things
which don't have utility
yeah so if you look at all the so-called
cognitive biases
they're all about reducing the energy
cost of making decisions
and on average they can like pan out
better
and reduction of energy cost is critical
in evolution
and particularly for humans because our
brain takes up so much energy
disproportionate
in many ways to its utility that we have
a problem
so klein's klein discovered that in
terms of the way that people did mental
rehearsal
and this contradicts some of white's
work because
klein and vike both work with what are
called crews
i people in mission critical
environments
and my own work basically argues that
the ritualization of becoming a crew
member
creates a cognitive trigger which
actually defines the way in which you
scan data
and the original project we did on that
was way back in new zealand
and where we were looking at safety and
lorry drivers
sorry truck drivers for the americans
amongst you
and we did that this was distributed
ethnography so we put
students into the cabs um
for three weeks gathering narrative on a
continuous basis and i'll talk more
about this in in the third
session yeah and how we do that key
thing is
this is a quantitative approach not a
qualitative approach
yeah my background is in physics i don't
buy qual
yeah it's you know quant matters right
and no social scientist ever has enough
data to form any valid conclusion
whatsoever so kind of like we're looking
at increasing the volume of data
so if i've got students act as
ethnographers in direct
observation of camp drivers i can get a
lot of data very quickly
and the principle was simple the lorry
driver could ask
just assume truck driver if you don't
get it i need to go back to vernacular
at this time of night right
so the lorry driver you know could ask
the student to do anything which was
legal we thought we'd put that
qualification in
right and in return for which kind of
like
you know that helped that built a
relationship so they started to own
things up
now that was a fascinating project one
is we found that amphetamine use was
about three times what people thought
and it turned out the main modulating
factor behind and i'm going to use
modulator rather than cause generally
the main modulating factor behind
amphetamine use was
actually the tachograph so it was the
device designed to control how you know
how many hours people drive which was
meant to make them safer
was actually producing crazy behavior
because if they hit within a certain
margin they just had to stop us leaking
the cap
you know when they could have gone on
for like 10 minutes and stayed somewhere
comfortable but they couldn't do that
because of the physical record yeah um
so that was interesting but
we also and it parallels work we've done
on safety in the northeast of england
which shows the main reason for mental
breakdown is the health and safety
regulation not the job
and that's working with what we call
blue light services
yeah because basically any formal system
and i now come into
the complexity thing any formal system
assumes you're in the center of a normal
distribution
whereas a substantial amount of life
happens in the tails of a pareto
distribution
so if you look at hospital safety
procedures they're based on single
morbidity
but most entries into and
multi-morbidity
and that that changes effectively the
distribution pattern the risk
so we found that but then we also found
that somewhere in the region of
80 percent of the accidents the off-road
accidents
were actually happening in the first 10
to 15 minutes after a lorry arrived at
the harbour
and the driver started to unload the
lorry
now nobody attracted that level of data
before but
that was significant and we speculated
and later proved that the reason was
very simple
they've been driving for 100 200 miles
yeah so the cognitive activation
patterns the patterns through which they
were scanning
or filtering available data were
effectively driver patterns
and it was taking the brain 10 to 15
minutes to reset itself as a loader
and therefore they were having the
classic sort of weightlifting type
accidents
and the intervention we did there which
catch accidents by two-thirds
was we got them all to strap on a heated
weight lifters belt
before they unpacked the lorry so we
created a ritual
to switch them from being driver to
loader and it was a physical ritual as
well that strapping on changed their
stance
and we associated the training with
strapping on the belt so there was only
one rule you don't unload to
strap on the belt yeah and because it
had heated gel pads
everybody wanted to strap it on anyway
because it was a really nice feeling
when you did it
and that made a significant difference
now that to me is quite important
because klein's work identified that as
well
vike tends to work tends to generalize
from the particular and this is a key
complexity principle
complexity recognizes that most things
are context specific
whereas the dominant approach in
management science until complexity long
complexity came along was to assume
context free
so this is where i'm gonna maybe or
maybe not get controversial but i really
don't apologize if i upset anybody with
this i'm happy to defend it all right
um what you actually see is people go
and you know
and invite did this a lot so if you look
at ficanzatcliff on on
forgotten name of the book he's got a
yellow cover
it's on mission critical systems anyway
right
and i think vik is a lot better when he
writes on his own i think when he's
writing with subcliff
the quality goes down a lot but that's
just a personal opinion
um but basically what he does he studies
people like aircraft carriers and
firefighters
um with the intent of discovering
what their characteristics are which
cause them to
share failure now anybody with any
background in knowledge management
knows that sharing failure is the most
critical thing
and it's the most difficult thing
because there's more learning in failure
than there is in success
but the consequences of failure of hives
so people won't do it
so if i discovered a group of people you
know i say
u.s navy personnel on carriers fire
fighters
who actually did share failures so he
went and studied them identified things
they had in common
and that was what was written up as
things you should do
now i remember the first time i read
that book and unfortunately i was at a
conference with its authors so i
probably shouldn't have said what i said
um and i remember sending that i said
but you
you've selected crews
yeah you selected environments in which
people wear uniform where they're highly
ritualized
yeah and i said i can replicate the
behavior of firefighters if i burn the
office down every morning but that's
probably not an acceptable management
practice
and just say that didn't go down very
well right
um but i stand by it right so this
context of context free context specific
one is a key one
um an understanding of context is
critical to actually
any type of sense making right and
you've got i mean this is generally part
of the property we've got the confusion
of correlation with causation which is a
real problem in social science
and the way i normally illustrate that
is if wales which is the country i come
from we have three million people
if we want to increase the number of
nobel prizes we win beheaded population
then all we actually have to do is
increase dark chocolate consumption
because if you didn't know it dark
chocolate consumption directly
correlates with nobel prizes behead of
population
over the last 30 years worldwide and
that's a much bigger sample than most
social scientists ever work with
and so it's kind of like a simple thing
and it's quite pleasurable i quite like
dark chocolate
so you know we we start that process
right so that confusion is
is a real problem um so what i started
to do and this was originally when i was
in ibm research
um was to focus instead on using natural
science as a constraint
you know i'll talk more about
constraints
um next time around when i talk about
kinevin right
because in complexity mapping
constraints
is probably the most important thing you
do
because constraints are ordered aspects
in general of a complex system and they
can be managed and changed
so one of the ways you actually manage a
complex system is to change the
constraints
so what i decided to do was to accept
natural science as a constraint
this matches in with constructive theory
and physics which is duecast and others
at cambridge
where they're trying to look at physics
from a whole systems point of view
rather than atomistic point of view
and the example i always give is the
moon and the satellite are both
subject to the laws of gravity that acts
as a constraint
but the energy cost of putting up a
satellite is a lot less than the energy
cost of putting up the moon
therefore that's more likely to happen
so
what that translates into is what does
natural science tell us about the nature
of systems the nature of interactions
the nature of human cognition yeah and
that is a constraint
we know that that gives us security
things will operate within that
constraint
or without that constraint these
constraints can be
internal or external yeah endo
against exoskeleton so basically
within those constraints yeah we've got
a degree of
predictability and then we can apply
methods
consistent with those constraints and
then develop them in practice
the old name for that is praxis yeah the
interaction of theory with practice
or is aristotle put it the interaction
of saphir and pranesis
you know practical wisdom with
theoretical wisdom and you can't like me
both
so that was the general approach we
adopted initially within ibm and then
subsequently when i left ibm
um which was about 16 years ago now
in terms of setting up cognitive edge
and then the canvas center
so that allows you to do better decision
making
under conditions of uncertainty so
the other point is if you live in
uncertain times and
one things i'm going to talk about on
the final session on this is the work
i'm doing
for the european union at the moment
because i'm writing their handbook on
crisis management
yeah using kinevic yeah and if there's
you know we live in very uncertain times
what happened in the past is not going
to give me predictive power for what
will happen in the future
yeah one of my favorite phrases is
hindsight is very valuable
but hindsight doesn't lead to foresight
but i do know that i can't change the
way that people make decisions
so i can't make people be rational at an
individual level
i can't get rid of inattentional
blindness
yeah you will see what you expect to see
and interestingly
if you're part of the seventeen percent
who do see the gorilla
you come to believe you were wrong when
you talk with the 83 percent who didn't
so if that's a scientific constraint
then i need to build systems which make
the 17
visible before they talk to the 83
percent
and make that available to senior
decision makers
right so you see where i'm going with
this all right
um i've got something which i know which
is true
so i can build methods and tools
associated with that
the other thing which comes in here
is a link between three bodies of theory
one is the losing epistemology in the
concept of an assemblage
and that is becoming more and more
important as a theoretical construct in
the health sector at the moment
uh in complexity something which is
called a strange attractor which most
people know is the lorenz butterfly
so there's a nothing ever follows the
same pathway but there is a pattern
which you can recognize
yeah and in narrative theory what's
called a trope
yeah i i really don't like the concept
of memes
um partly because i think dawkins is an
idiot
right um and i've yet to find a single
geneticist who takes him remotely
seriously
um i mean the idea that the gene is
seeking to replicate itself is a form of
anthropomorphization
which is quite dangerous um and if
anybody hasn't
written read mary mitchelly's book
science and poetry
um she's one of the great british
philosophers she's one of those group of
female philosophers who were at oxford
during the war
when there weren't any males around
there's a whole group of them
yeah and scum midgley and others
um dawkins actually changed the
introduction to selfish gene to try and
combat her attack on him
because she basically said he was trying
to create a biological justification for
thatcher and reagan
and he got quite upset by that um
the reality is and and the mean metaphor
comes across which is actually quite
dangerous right there isn't a single
story or narrative seeking to replicate
itself
um what we see in human decision makers
is a whole body of anecdotes so
i tell a story you tell a story i like
your story so i tell similar stories
yeah and on the internet that happens
much faster
yeah and then those stories form what in
english is called a trope
yeah and it reaches a critical mass and
it goes through a phase shift
and then the trope or the assemblage or
the strange attractor
exists independently of the storyteller
yeah and people effectively get sucked
into it yeah they can't escape from it
and then they start to filter data
because the assemblage is a cognitive
activation pattern
and this is the problem i keep trying to
explain this i mean for my many and
various sins i have to read trump's
tweets every morning
um and what trump is doing
is to just catalyze tropes
he's not making a rational argument he's
using key phrases effectively to
capitalize the trope
and every time a boston brahmin or a
well-meaning liberal
argues against him logically they make
the trump more they make the trope worse
because all of the things that they say
the trope has has already evolved to
deal with those
as a conspiracy theory or as that's what
they say or they don't care
and so on and so forth yeah
now that was driven home to me um
i don't think i told this story last
time but it dares returning anyway
so i was in during the last presidential
election i was in california
um having dinner with kent beck and got
invited to a
champagne or cyanide party uh which
fortunately i didn't go to because if i
had to drink the cyanide i think
um and the next day i flew over to dc
and got pulled into a crisis level
meeting
um i've done a lot of work with the
intelligence community over the years in
fact
all of this stuff started when i was
working with john poindexter
um in darpa so i know a lot of those
guys so i was a foreigner i was you know
expert i got pulled in i've never seen
the
cia the fbi and the state department all
worked together before in my life but
they were all together now
this was kind of like you know the sort
of deep state in action
and i think halfway through it's kind of
what the hell did we do i said well
you guys just didn't make the case and
they said you don't understand their bad
it is
so three of us got put into a helicopter
and flown west i still don't know to
this day where we went
yeah and we were put in a lot given a
higher cartel to drive 50 miles north
and going to a designated bar
um our cover story was we were european
tourists
and we were told to go into the bar and
argue against trump
and i remember they said to me you know
don't worry about
it you're quite safe we're going to have
armed officers in the bar and i wasn't
worried about it until they said that
um so either way we go through this all
right we go into the bar i've drawn the
short straw
um there's an american football match
yeah
on the television so i decided i'm going
to go down the sports route
yeah um i'm welsh all right we play a
real sport called rugby you know it kind
of like goes on for long periods of time
and
offense has to become defense and you
don't wear lots of padding
so i'm now playing the sort of male game
here of that's not a real sport look at
all the padding
yeah and what you know you you know
what's going on
right in the course of that i
established that i teach at west point
which i do
you know i teach just war theory at west
point every now and then
so that gave me credibility right and
it's all going really well drinks have
been bought you know it's classic
male sort of bonding type stuff and then
i started to use a socratic technique
and the delight of philosophy is you're
trained in socratic questioning
but you tend to forget what happened to
socrates when the people of athens got
fed up with it all right
so i start the socratic technique and
after i've got him to contradict himself
three times yeah this was their leader
he walked away from the bar and
everything's gone quiet now
yeah and he turned around he put both
hands up with two fingers
and he said you you bastard that's
your education talking
yeah and i've never forgotten that
that's your education
talking and i remember we then went back
to dc and i said okay guys i get it now
yeah this is a fundamental
it's a it's a fundamental trope that
people are not going to escape from
now some of the things i'll talk about
in the future session this is kind of
like a
general introduction to the field uh
something in complexity which is called
the adjacent possible
so if you want to disrupt a deeply
negative attractor
then you find an adjacent attractor
which is weaker and you make it stronger
because then things will move across
this is called vector theory of change
so you don't say where you want to be
you say
we could go there next in fact one of
the key lessons of complexity
is that we start journeys with a sense
of direction
we don't have goals and that contradicts
nearly everything which has come out of
systems thinking for the past
four decades which kind of like wants to
have goals objectives vision statements
purpose all these sort of phrases yeah
you can only have those if you've got
material linear causality
yeah all of that implies that the future
is definable
um in a complex adaptive system
you don't have linear material causality
yeah you have don't even really have
teleological
causality either what you've got is
what's called dispositionality
so i can say the current dispositional
state of the system is
x yeah and i can say
these things are therefore unlikely to
happen
and these things are more likely to
but i can never say this will happen or
if we do
this we will get that result
so that leads into this key principle of
complexity
is we start journeys we don't try and
achieve goals
and if you start a journey with a sense
of direction
you're open to novelty on the pathway
if you have very specific goals you
don't see the things which create that
and that's creating a whole new form of
measurement
i can get quite practical now there's a
thing called good hearts law which you
might have come across
um famous british economist good hearts
law states
that any statistical instrument used for
policy loses all value
that was rephrased by marilyn stratham
who is a really fierce british
anthropologist
do not cross marilyn you won't live yeah
as the minute of measure becomes a
target it ceases to be a measure
because what you get is gaming behavior
which is what you get with goals
so the whole principle about starting
journeys and seeking the adjacent
possible like stepping stones
and measuring that and a vector measure
is direction and speed of travel for
intensity of effort
i'll repeat that a vector measure is
direction
and speed for energy
it's it's a balance between those three
we're now using that for example to
measure
um the impact of nurses on patient
health
in kobe because actually
at the moment the average british
hospital has
over a thousand outcome based targets
with 15 percent of them the money going
on managing the measurement system
rather than providing health care
we can replace about 80 percent of those
with patients keeping journals and
nurses keeping journals
measuring the attractor wells the
dispositional states
and measuring whether you're moving
things in the right direction
okay so when and that to my mind i mean
the american equivalent of this is the
educational system
yeah in which measurement is destroying
any hope
for people from deprived backgrounds and
i've done a lot of field ethnography in
the projects in new york
and it's the formalism and the the
measurement system of the educational
system
which is designed to improve things
which is actually holding people back
it means teachers who actually inspire
kids
are generally punished teachers you're
good at completing learning plans aren't
yeah another example on this i'm going
to stop and open up for questions yeah
this is kind of a general introduction
my daughter who is now 31 an
anthropologist and working for me
which is quite scary because she also
acts as a shop steward for all my other
research assistants
i get this phone call with addie's told
us we're not to put up with this anymore
and variations on the theme um
but she's a she won the university prize
for the best master's thesis
um she wrote it on the on episode on
uh assemblage theory strange attractors
in the anthropology of male diabetes um
and she's going on to mental health in
those areas
um either way so i lived with her
through her ba and then her mma
yeah and i hope one these days to live
through a phd but she wants to study
mental health
and being as i was one of the subjects
for a master's thesis so professors
think she's waiting for me to become a
subject for the
phd right at least that's the standard
joke
right um and it was fun because it's my
subject
you know the internet means i can chat
with her while she's in lectures i can
feed the questions we have a lot of fun
disrupting things yeah
in the way that fathers and daughters do
but the first assay she wrote
for when she was an undergraduate
actually picked up the theme for which
she won the university prize five years
later
but her assay failed
and i still remember you know picking
her up alright she was in tears and i
said look ellie you wrote something
original
you're not allowed to do that at the
undergraduate level
yeah the lecturer has got a marking plan
yeah and they're ticking you off against
the marking plan and you have to work
that out
because that's the way you're going to
get good essay grades
and i said that's actually a really bad
thing which has happened to education
and i still remember the first essay i
wrote um
and this is british philosophy in the
1970s
and it got sent back and the professor
had written on it
this is metaphysics not philosophy
please rewrite it
so i sent it back with metaphysics his
philosophy please mark it
and we sort of carried on like that for
three years right
and i got quite a lot of a grades
because i never
broke the marketing plan i just had
interesting ideas and i was a generalist
so i was putting in things from other
fields
and they quite liked that because it
livened up what that was otherwise a
boring evening but i would not survive
that in a modern university yeah so
we're rewarding people who are game
players and that means if i look at
things like black lives matter and the
like
we're actually rewarding people who are
educated to pass educational games
yeah rather than rewarding people who've
got original thoughts and can actually
develop in different ways
so i'm coming back to where i started in
the question
what complexity theory does is it
basically says
most of the way that systems thinking
has worked for the past three decades
only applies where the level of
constraint is such
that you've got a predictable
relationship between cause and effect
either system is ordered
when you haven't got that level of
constraint none of those methods apply
anymore
and you have to develop different
methods and tools and that's where i
focus
so i'll come back to that definition i
started with
how do i make sense of the world so that
i can act in it
right now with that comes the concept of
sufficiency
so it's how do i know enough or how
do i know when i know enough to act
and of course the nature of the action
could be anything from a definitive
act to a series of parallel
safe to failed experiments yeah to a
mass engagement or
what we call a sensor probe and i go
through those when i go through
connecting
um next week yeah so that concept of
what does it mean to act
and what does it mean to know and when
is that knowledge sufficient
and the concept of being
context-specific not context-free
you know all of those are coming out of
this basic complexity science-based
approach to sense-making
you know i've spoken for 40 odd minutes
there so it's definitely time for
wider contribution and i forgot when did
he stop by the way
cahill when do we stop oh we're supposed
to stop with three right
but i guess i'm relaxed
okay no that was great that's so much
yes i haven't eaten that i haven't had
the gin and tonic yet and it's already
yeah no
that was amazing um so much to chew on
there wow
i forgot to say it everyone that um you
know you guys should put the questions
in the chat but you guys
already knew that and to keep it clean
in the chats too
um but yeah that was great i really like
your emphasis on
the relationship between nodes rather
than the attributes of the nodes
themselves
um i think that's a really key key point
uh but yeah it's the key thing an
organizational change and i think it's
also an ethical thing
every attempt people make to change
people
yeah it's not going to work and be it's
wrong
but changing how people connect is
something which is ethically valid and
will actually produce change faster
yeah i actually have a selfish question
because i'm i'm a
i guess i'm like an urbanist i guess or
i like urban studies and uh one of the
things that
i'd like to talk about is the impact of
the built environment on
relationships i'm wondering if you come
across
any insights of yourself on that or
if that rings brings up anything for you
we're doing a fair amount of work on
this in singapore
singapore's interesting i mean when i
left ibm the head of the civil service i
i've got a huge amount of respect for
the civil service in singapore
uh if you don't know they have an elite
educational system which is entirely
meritocratic
if you come from a poor family and
you're bright you're going to end up
in that elite program yeah the whole
educational system is geared towards it
and the bright guys all become civil
servants they don't go into industry
and i remember that the head of the
civil service peter hoe is a brilliant
guy
said two things to me he said one is
there's some very interesting ideas here
but you're not going to get it right up
front so i'll give you a series of
projects because i want to be around
when it works
and i can't think of any other civil
servant in any other country in the
world who would ever say that i'll take
that risk
but it was encouraged yeah um
the the big thing that we've been one of
the latest latest things we've been
working on there is the
built environment because
singapore know two or three things first
of all
they're within two or three decades of
having to have their whole hop
having to have their whole population in
air conditioning for several hours a day
yeah yeah and malaysia is going to
suffer mass casualties and major
immigration because
the temperature is going to be
consistently above 55 degrees fahrenheit
at which point the body can't shed heat
fast enough
yeah so they're preparing for that
unlike most cities around the world
and some of the stuff we're looking at
there is actually increasing the size of
the social space but reducing the
personal space
because if you look at the studies on
aggressive behavior on rats
close confinement in public spaces yeah
it can actually trigger the changes so
we need to make the public spaces more
than the private spaces
yeah in that sort of sense so that's
been the path
and they're thinking long term in that
respect i think
there are lots of other things on that i
think
an example one of the things they did in
the uk in the 70s
we used to have to walk or used to have
what were called two up two downs
so two two rooms on the ground floor two
rooms on the top floor
in long terraced rows of houses yeah
with the toilet in a sort of shed in the
back
in colloquial english called the kazi
yeah
um yeah and if you had to walk down the
garden at 1963 when it was bloody
freezing cold all right you you kind of
knew about that
um but those were real communities and
then in
the white house heat of the
technological revolution to quote tony
then
they basically demolished all of those
and built tower blocks which were
designed to be perfect living
environments for each other
and of course they destroyed the
community they destroyed the
dependencies they destroyed the
interaction
and those are now mostly slums with high
levels of violence
yeah and you don't go down the lifts on
your own late at night
yeah so i think one of the things
and i i remember going to cumbernaut
which is a brand new town in scotland
which is now one of the major areas for
crime
but the architects had designed it for
the way they thought people
should live rather than building things
on the way that people did live
right so i think there's a whole body of
work
yeah around that we need to think about
right i mean
those would be some example
yeah thank you yeah well yeah i did an
exchange in singapore
and in the us and it was really
interesting to me
meet some of those people there um
singapore is still a democracy whereas
the u.s hasn't been for a few years
well some would argue that it's a you
know it's a pseudo democracy but
but i get your point actually they're
really they're really trying to get
opposition mps elected at the moment
they're really worried that the workers
party don't have enough but
yeah people are quite happy with the way
singapore is run and you don't have to
have be a billionaire to get elected to
their parliament
yeah that's called a rotten borough in
in democratic terms
okay so uh are you able to stay like 10
or 15 minutes extra
i do if you want okay okay perfect um
so yeah we have a lot of questions um
trying to keep up but we have peter
jones with us here
uh peter jones do you have a question
you have a question
no thanks hi dave really enjoy
uh listening to you again i've got a
question relative to
kind of the conceit or the position of
the stoa that is
um you know know your work on
multi-ontology sense making
it's a it's an excellent framework that
i think helps
as a as a reference for sorting out
ontological and epistemological
positions
and ways of of interacting and knowing
um how they might cross in communication
and so the in the store there's it's
kind of launched with this position of
the time of meta crisis
with hardened positions in this crisis
arising in memetic tribes
and so in these mimetic tribes are
you know the different trope tribes that
we're shunted into these can be seen as
micro ontologies
right they're ways that we're we
identify ourselves and hold not just to
the tribe but all the positions that go
along with it
and they could blend but we're kept in
our swim lanes by this kind of new
tribalism social media
um propaganda reinforcers so we've got
this world of strong norms
and people are butting up against each
other's positions all the time
my question would be then given
maldiantology sense-making or how that
might evolve
how do we break out of these these
strong normative lanes while holding
our reputations not getting canceled how
can we communicate
um within these expectation loops
to help to help ourselves and help
others blend ontologies
in a you know i mean it takes some risk
right how do we
how do we help um i don't know if it's a
change in a way of thinking about your
framework or using that in a way that
we might communicate better to loosen
the hold of these tribal mental models
i think there's some things we can bring
in straight straight away one is
we have a massive problem with the
internet because the internet is an
unbuffered feedback loop
if you have an unbuffered feedback loop
then perversion will come
faster and it will be more or less
unstoppable if you remember what
happened with automatic trading
algorithms which caused the stock
exchange to crash it's the same
principle
so one of the programs which we're still
trying to get funding for but we've now
done in sweden colombia
singapore egypt and elsewhere
is to use children as ethnographers
through their schools into their
communities on a continuous basis
so we put human interpretation and human
validation of data
rather than the classic black box this
is kind of like called rich data as
opposed to thick data or big data
yeah so we increase the human buffering
in the system
which also increases the empathy the
other thing we've also been doing there
which
i'm quite proud of is what we call
transgenerational pairing
so that's linking young people with
people in their grandparents generation
to come up with local initiatives so
trying to get away from grand
initiatives to local initiatives locally
generated
now again that was science-based because
we know that brain plasticity
yeah kinda like unless you're
traumatized it kind of like stops in
your early 20s and doesn't start again
until your 50s
so if you want innovation you need to be
under 25 or over 50.
you don't get much between the two and
they kind of like really i know every
everybody's going to like this one of
these days right
but it's actually quite interesting
innovation in the sciences is under 25
in the humanities it's generally when
you're older
because and the evolutionary argument is
because it's synthesis
not flashes of genius it's the ability
to bring things together
which is what the humanities is about
right
so if you look in evolutionary terms we
have the longest period of training of
any mammal
so there's very high levels of
plasticity up until
two in fact as far as we can see some of
your neocortex
processing is actually done by your
carers
until too yeah we don't quite know the
mechanism for it yet but it's actually
why if you don't get the right level of
nurture in those first two years
there are capacities which you never get
a chance to develop again
it's an absolutely critical period um as
you start to hit puberty the brain
starts to lock down because you've got
to go and hunt for the tribe
yeah and whatever the prejudices of the
tribe you'll adopt
you actually don't see racism in kids
and before puberty
yeah but it comes in big time after
puberty
right and then interestingly chemically
triggered male or female
you know mid 40s 50s it becomes plastic
again
and the argument is if you survive to
that age and have to gather a tribe
you've got something about you which the
tribe needs but you better bloody will
stop leading it because you're not fit
enough anymore so you go and sit around
the campfire and look after the kids and
teach them
yeah so we've replicated that you know
15 transgenerational pairs
if they come up with a good idea they're
put into a trio with somebody from
government who makes their ideas work
so we're using technology as a connector
but we're increasing human buffering in
the system
right so that's key the other thing
which i'll probably talk about next week
is we've brought heavily on board in the
latest release of canavin
um the concept of apparea
all right and the apparatic okay
now remember the basic concept of our
career yeah
is that it's the end result that oh the
only decision which is ever made is
where you don't know what decision you
can make everything else is a process
so the deliberate shift into an
apparatic state
yeah a conscious apparatic state and
then the ontological shift from that
and that's actually all written up in
the eu handbook on crisis management
i'll go through that here is you
basically in a crisis what you do is you
do radical sudden draconian imposition
of constraints
yeah the new zealand prime minister did
this brilliantly she could have got it
wrong
but and that's okay but it was better to
do it then because she couldn't wait the
british and the americans waited
when they imposed it it was kind of like
too late to make a massive difference so
you know you're going to get a lot of
this wrong but you you basically make
decisions fast to increase your options
space downstream
yeah and that gives you the time to go
into the apparatic state and then you've
got
you know four different movements one is
those experts you were ignoring who you
now would know were right we'll call
them in apologize give them some cash
if you've got competition between
experts like in
behavioral scientists against
epidemiologists which was a big issue
in the uk then you ritualize the
confrontation
yeah to resolve it if you know the
hypothesis about what you should do you
run
parallel safe to fair experiments about
the hypotheses
if you don't think you've covered off
the hypotheses then you do a mass
sensing thing over a multi-sensor
network
from multiple perspectives in order to
identify the hypotheses
now if you look what i've done there
i've got a simple stage plan
which is all about awareness all right
what you're trying to do is to shift
decision makers to be aware
that there are systems where they can't
have the right answer
not only can't they have the right
answer but if they do think they've got
the right answer they're 90
certain to be wrong and and this is why
a lot of us are pretty pissed off with
talent because talent blocks anybody who
doesn't worship at his feet
and i'm proud to have been blocked by
talib all right i mean this is i'm
trying to get blocked by trump as well
and i've got the complete card set of
arrogant bastards right
um and you know you've got people like
didier's work
in um in zurich which is much better but
the concept of the fat tail is key
because fundamentally in the center of a
normal distribution you can use
inductive logic
which means you can create predictions
but in the tails of a pareto
distribution
you've got to up take an abductive not
an inductive approach
okay now abduction is yes goes back to
quine right this is the
the logic of hunches now the challenge i
was given by poindexter when i went to
work for him in darpa and just to be
clear i'm a wealth socialist
um i didn't know who he was until i
decided i liked him and then i
discovered i wasn't meant to like him
but i'm afraid i've got a lot of respect
for john
john
yeah well he had two programs he had tia
which he got into trouble with the
congress with he had genoa too which i
ran with meredith
which was the human side people forget
about that one he had two bets
yeah and i remember him saying when he
was nsa
um every time he asked for advice all
the a
all the agencies competed to have their
advice accepted not to tell him what he
needed to know
and i've validated that with two other
nsa since one democrat one republican
so he said your job is to find a way in
which i can go directly from an abstract
representation to the raw data without
interpretation
okay and that's called disintermediation
now that's key to changing people yeah
the big thing we're working on at the
moment is to entangle a politician
with the lives of people who vote for
them so they can see
empathetic resonance that's our next big
project
yeah and without in without being
buffered by interpretive layers
so there's a lot of things we can do we
just need to do them at scale
thank you for that okay so we have a lot
of plus ones on
i'll just call anjan
you have a question you'd like to ask
you could only just often ask or
would you like me to um let me find my
question
um
it would be useful by the way to have a
copy of the chats because i can look at
those before next week
that sort of form in what i mean today
was designed to be quite open and chat
and then the next three a bit more
structured so i'm sort of working out
what i put into those
cool i'll get them for you i've found my
question
um what what are some systems or
institutions that by conventional
thinking
are considered broken or failed but
under a complexity framework you see
they
they do things well
um i'm not sure i fully heard it but let
me answer what i think i've heard and
then you can tell me how wrong it was
all right
i think there's some interesting
examples here jury trial is broken
um but there are actually better ways of
doing that um
one of the things we're we're trying to
work on an experiment with at the moment
is to have four juries of three people
in separate rooms
and if three of the four agree the
person is guilty or innocent
yeah so you start you stop the phenomena
of 12 people in a room being dominated
by one personality
so that's taking a complexity
perspective right
um i think the other thing which is
completely shot at the moment is
democracy
um democracy in the form most of us know
it
evolved in in england in the 19th
century
you know with the great reformats and it
was based on a small population where
people could know who they were voting
for
yeah so there was and people regularly
crossed the floor so people changed
party allegiance there was
a lot of flux yeah by the 1950s and 60s
yeah the population was so big that
people voted for a slate they didn't
vote for a person
because they couldn't know them and
people always you know in order to be in
parliament you had to be in a political
party and you kind of like chose the one
at university based on who was going to
be there
um so you've got that sort of problem
yeah and i go back to the american
constitution
if you go back to the founding fathers
they said nobody should be elected to
the poster president by the popular vote
because we'll get despots and populists
yeah and the holy actual college which
you find some people you trust and they
go away and pick somebody to be
president
because we give them a lot of powers
yeah so i think
there's some and there are issues there
on the you know
the number of acquaintances you can
maintain is about 150.
um once a population goes above about
five million it loses cultural cohesion
and it gets fractious
so there's a whole body of stuff we know
there in terms of looking at for example
delegative democracy rather than one
person one vote
yeah um and the perversion is high i
mean i think america is the only country
in the world where you can advertise
your services to stop
people voting and you don't get
imprisoned to put in prison for it
yeah so you know the the the democracy
is shot at the moment
right and you know we're working with
extinction rebellion which is really
interesting
um because they're going through the
same sort of factional fights that left
went through in the
70s yeah yeah the monty python
life of brian people's front of judea is
regrettably still
present in the ecological movement right
so we're trying to change that
right but one things we're doing with
them and some others is we're looking at
how can we involve the whole of the
population in the citizen jury and we've
already done that in wales
or in the citizen assembly
um but the trouble is at the moment
everybody's jumping into new ways of
making decisions without having the raw
science they're just doing what they
think works or copying what somebody
else did
and that ain't gonna work because it
won't scale i mean one of the classic
mistakes people make in the middle east
is we confuse we confuse gifts with
bribes
the middle east is based around a
gifting culture but from a western
perspective it looks like a bribe
and so we end up making the thing
corrupt because we don't understand the
way it works
in the west we have an equivalent if you
belong to the right golf club you're
going to get contracts
yeah the way darpa money is adequate
happy i've got i've had darpa contracts
it's very simple
you get invited to a hotel for two days
you pay for your own time you talk about
the solution
if they like what you say they write the
rfp to exactly match what you said so
you get the contract
that's how darpa works
because you need the human judgment
element within the system
so this question about a new this is why
might have sounds making is called
naturalizing sense making
it's like naturalizing epistemology it's
the base sense making in the natural
sciences not the social sciences
okay um so yeah we're just going to
do one more question i'm sorry everyone
else
but i'm gonna call on rain uh
yeah rin would you like to ask your
question
yeah um thanks dave this is really
amazing
um i had a question i'll try to make it
relevant for everybody
it's really about distributed cognition
but some of the things you were
mentioning
remind me of edwin hutchins work and i
honestly haven't
uh read any um
cognitive ethnography since reading
hutchins so i'm just curious
uh how that influences your work and
where's the overlap with
either cognitive ethnography or
distributed cognition
cognition in the world is in that
bookshelf behind me those are the books
i keep going back to and reading
all right um yeah i mean i think the the
way we do it with human systems
is that and there are several things
human beings are brilliant at gaming
so the thing a human being will do if
you ask them a question
is they'll work out what answer you want
and they'll either give you that answer
or they'll give you the opposite that's
kind of like the basic response
yeah so one of the things we developed
and this was
when that we were dealing with the
problem from that john sent me which is
how do you objectify abduction
so how is one person's intuitively more
accurate than somebody else's
intuitively
yeah and the way we did that was to
create what's called high abstraction
signification
which is you interpret data but you
can't know
what the right answer is and the method
of interpretation creates a cognitive
load
so you flip from what's called autonomic
processing to what's called novelty
receptive processing in real science
or if you read economists who didn't
bother to walk across to the corridor
and ask their neuroscience colleagues
earlier
thinking fast and thinking slow
we knew everything that he found in that
book before he found it
but people just don't work across
disciplines because that way you go
deeper
all right so that's the cognitive load
aspect so if i get
5000 people to interpret the same data
in the same time slot in a way in which
they don't know what the right answer is
i can draw fitness landscapes from that
which so the general pattern of belief
and show the outlier beliefs and others
and interesting we
we originally developed this in the
concept of conflict resolution in
colombia and i'm now using exactly the
same techniques on
conflict resolution in maternity
services in scotland
which to be quite honest is a lot ham a
lot harder and more dangerous than
handling the farc
right um but you got this tension
between surgeons who want all women at
six months put into a hospital so
there's no risk of anything going wrong
but they've got all their super
equipment yeah and women in their
families who quite like quite
like to be in a local hospital and
remember this is islands of scotland
where you're two days from a hospital
and stuff like that
the way we're handling that is all the
groups are presenting their summary
then every other group will interpret
everybody else's summaries and then
we'll produce
overlaid contour maps which so where
they're agreed
where the disagreement is so extreme
they can't talk about it
and where there are outlier clusters of
agreement by which we can make a change
that's distributed cognition yeah
um it's and and if you've got it and
i've argued for a very long time and
this is where i would depart slightly
from hutchins
is human beings aren't ants this is what
i keep saying down at santa fe and they
get all upset about this because
human beings have to be ants for their
models to work
yeah um human beings have intelligence
we have multiple identities we have
intentionality
um human decision making is a level of
complexity
well above anything that you see in the
wild we're the only species to show
empathy outside the kinship group for
example and that's significant
yeah um i think i mentioned this last
time but
terry's brilliant book on radical
sacrifice is worth reading
uh human beings understand the necessity
and role of sacrifice
and that that's that we can build on so
you've got to build
distributed cognition systems which
recognize those unique aspects of humans
excellent excellent um thank you thank
you so much dave
i'm gonna pass it over to peter uh to
just close out this session but i just
want to say thanks again and
thanks for the questions and they will
be back again so
um if you have any burning questions i
know some people had some
burning questions my medic keeper uh
rosa albert
bring them next time and hopefully we
can get to them
cool thank you uh cleal for mcn um dave
just you want to set up next week or any
final thoughts before i make some
announcements
my plan next week is to do the basic
canadian framework the concept of the
apparatic and liminal
and constraints so i'll have some slides
next week sorry but
i can't draw in this virtual environment
yeah very cool all right so i'll make
some
closing announcements in a moment but uh
dave thank you so much for coming
to the stoa for the sensemaker in
residence series uh the first one for
september um
for her upcoming events of the stoa you
can go to the soa.ca i just post in the
chat
we have a discord so if you want to
continue this conversation right now you
can just go to the discord go to
the rules section give it a thumbs up
and then all the other channels opened
up and there's video chats and stuff
like that
sign up for the mailing list and if
you'd like to support the stoa you can
go to our patreon page
to continue having amazing events like
this
tomorrow we have uh
student of the human condition uh peter
wang he's doing a series on mental
models he's another sense maker
residence in september that's uh
tomorrow at 10 a.m eastern time
and we have uh joe norman doing a
session on
applied complexity um and that's
september
10th at 10 p.m eastern time we might
even have an essence
join the stoa so maybe there's some
crossover here with uh snowden and
and the man himself so we'll see about
that
uh that being said thank you david and
everyone for coming to the store today